Guide to the Carl Degler Papers SC1100
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Carl N. Degler papers
circa 1920s-2016
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Degler, Carl N.
Roark, James L.
SC1100
17 Linear Feet (13 boxes and 148 megabytes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The materials were a gift of Carl N. Degler, 2010; Tess Degler, 2015; James L. Roark, 2016.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Carl Neumann Degler is an American historian. Degler is a past president of the Organization of American Historians, the American Historical Association and the Southern Historical Association. He is the Margaret Byrne Professor of American History Emeritus at Stanford University.
In 1972, Degler was awarded the Pulitzer Prize for History for his book Neither Black nor White, a work comparing slavery and race relations in Brazil and the United States. He wrote Out of Our Past, a study of United States history. In 1986 Degler was elected President of the American Historical Association.
Related Materials
An oral history interview conducted by Glenna Matthews is available at San Jose State University: http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt8k40382g/.
Scope and Contents
Materials include correspondence, research files, drafts, and travel materials, among others.
United States -- History -- Study and teaching (Higher).; Race relations -- History.; Degler, Carl N.; Roark, James L.; Degler, Carl N.
- Research notecards "Gettysburg + Biology and Culture II" (Box 1)
  United States -- History -- Study and teaching.; Stanford University -- Faculty.; Degler, Carl N.
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2010-077
  - Fortenbaugh Lecture, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Fortenbaugh Lecture (2) - One Among Many; The Civil War in Comparative Perspective (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Overview Essay & Chapters (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Delta Queen Lectures (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Historical Explanation (Causality), 1987-88 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Unionism - Confederacy, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 1 - Darwinian Impact, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 2 - Beyond the Darwinian Imperative (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 3 - Laying the Foundation (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 4 - Kroeber (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chapter 5 - Sexism (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapter 6 - Decoupling Behavior (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapter 7 - Decoupling From Race (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapter 8 - Triumph of Culture (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chapter 9 - Return to Biology (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapter 10 - Incest Chapter (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chapter 11 - Uses of Biology (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chapter 12 - Biology and the Nature of Females (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chapter 13 - Uses of Biology Theory (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chapter 14 - Epilogue (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Commonwealth Lecture, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lecture: Entering Newera (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Southern: Presidential Address (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - AHA Pres. Address, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - University of Illinois Book (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Angermann's Paper, Etc., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Burden of Am. History, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - German History, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - German History (2) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - German Institute Lecture`, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Germany v U.S.: Total War, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Total War: Essay Etc., 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - What Does History Do For Us? (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Paley Lectures (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Talk: Unity & Diverisity, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Plans for Book, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Darwinians Confront Gender, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Historiography Essay, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Paley Lecture I (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Paley Lecture II (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Paley Lecture III and "Darwin Remembered" (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Darwinian Cooperation, etc., 1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Social History Essay (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sociobiology Project (Old), 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - New Reading on Ethology and Darwin, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Essay on Sociobiology, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sociobiology Essay - NEW, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Evolution and History, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sociobiology, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Biology and Society, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Darwinism: Lecture, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Race, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Animals, Machines, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Multi-Culturism, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Southern Families, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sociobiology, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence on Sociobiology, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Other South Individuals (Box 4)
  - Biology and Culture (Box 4)
  - Notes for Book and Bibliography A-F (Box 4)
  - Notes on Race, Social Darwinism, etc. (Box 4)
- Memorial service, 2015-03-07; Accession ARCH-2015-074; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
- Remembering Carl Degler: Pioneering Scholar and Pioneering Feminist, 2016-01-09; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
  Scope and Contents
  American Historical Association Session 196: Remembering Carl Degler: Pioneering Scholar and Pioneering Feminist.
  Saturday, January 9, 2016: 2:30 PM-4:30 PM Grand Ballroom D (Hilton Atlanta, Second Floor)
  Chair: Richard Wightman Fox, University of Southern California
  Panel: William H. Chafe, Duke University Linda K. Kerber, University of Iowa James T. Kloppenberg, Harvard University Glenna Matthews, independent scholar
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2016-055
  - Corresponding on textbook (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Final bits (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Material related to Vassar (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - unlabeled (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Darwin (notes for talks) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Darwinism, then, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rise and Fall of Darwinism (S.F. talk/Dennett) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Darwinian Imperative (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Darwinism lectures (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters in Parchial schools (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lectures (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Missouri Lecture Evolutionary Theory and history (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Stanford History (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - OAH Session, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brazil and U.S.A (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chicago Darwin Conference (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chicago (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Darwin Religion (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Darwinism - Talks Pieces (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Comparative liberalism (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Vassar file (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Race, Culture, and Biology paper (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lecture: limits necessity of history (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Richmond Conference (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hodgson Essay (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Personal Docs (Historical, sentimental, etc) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Race, culture, biology, correspondence, etc (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lincolhn Darwin (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lecture: history (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - History evolutionary theory (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - History and theory piece (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lecture" Exorcising Racism (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Essay on US Politics (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Chinese talks (ACLS) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Civil War as Consequence, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - German (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Royalty Statements: Harper, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Carl's personal (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ripon college diploma (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Carl Degler Obituary Material (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stanford (correspondence contracts, etc) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Carl's memorial service program, 2015 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs from Vassar (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Remembering Carl Degler AHA in Atlanta, 2016 Jan 9 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Florida (other south) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - New Introd: other south (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Place over time: reviews royalties new contract (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book on Women and the Family; correspondence (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Materials on C.P. Gilman (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pulitzer Prize in History (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bancroft (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - unlabeled (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - St. Cat's trip (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Russian trip (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mexico trip (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Italian trip (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Trip to Spain, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - unlabeled (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Carl's Ph.D. Dissertation, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Reviews: At odds (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Professional Meetings (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Transcript of CND interview, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - South African Trip (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Prague, etc Trip (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Ecuador, trip to (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - unlabeled (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Degler, 1977-1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - unlabeled (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Other south-correspondence (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Scott - Foresman - Royalty Statements (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Scott Foresman, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Book Out of Our Past (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Xenophobia lecture (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Civil War and German War of Unification (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lecture: social: civil war (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lecture: why did the suffrage take so long, 1980 Sep (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Voice of America talk, 1973 Jan (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Duke lecture, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Talks on in search (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - German H.I (Darwinism correspond), 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - A German Conference, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lecture: multiculturalism, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notre Dame lecture and correspondence, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Florida lecture (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Memphis talk (Lincoln v Bishark) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Angermann, Erich, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Permissions granted, 1972-1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Slavery compared (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Women shaping the family, 1988 Jun 10 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Presidency: paper, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Vanderbilt essay, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Women and politics (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Business, 1997 Apr-1993 Feb (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jack Rakove's nomination, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gordon Wright Memorial (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence on book (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mosher survey (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Business, 1987-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - reprints or copies of CND's arts, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Carl's professional memories and docs (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Roman Africa, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Carl's brochure Stanford trip, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Feminist meeting, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Gettysburg lecture Lincoln prize, 1987-1992 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Harmsworth, 1973-1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Philips club (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Hearing aids (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - University Sem. (V. Fuchs), 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - AHA presidential trips etc, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Business, 1984-1990 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Trip to England, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - USIA lecture and correspondence, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Women's sexuality paper correspondence (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Materials for childrens stories (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Potter (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Neither black nor white royalty statements (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Out of our past-revisions and correspondence (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Writing plans reviews, 1965-1979 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Scalice case, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Ideas for talks (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 2nd essays, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Christmas Letters copies, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Christmas Letters old (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Hellen Allen event (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, misc, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Old letters etc to respond to CND (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Trip to Chile, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - unlabeled (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - India trip, 1967-1977 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - China trip (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - European trip (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - unlabeled (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Brazil: trip to, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Scotland and Stuttgart, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Sweden trip etc, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Israel, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Germany, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Holocaust "jokes" paper (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Nation piece, 1980 Aug 19 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Professional meetings correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reviews: in search (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Personal history notes (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - University of Utah correspondence (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Vassar correspondence and contracts, 1952-1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Alumnus of the Year award Upsula College, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2017-070
  - Correspondence between James L. Roark and Carl N. Degler, 1972-1991 (Box 1)
  - To Carl from Otis L. Graham, 1991-4-19 (Box 1)